<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessedness of good men after death a sermon preach'd at the funeral of the Revd. Mr. Henry Cornish, B.D., who died on Sunday, Decemb. 18th, in the eighty ninth year of his age and was interred on Thursday, Decemb. 22d, 1698, in the Church of Bisiter, in the County of Oxford : with a preface to rectifie some misrepresentations &amp;c. in a late pamphlet, entitled Some remarks on the life, death, and burial of the said Mr. Cornish / by John Ollyffe ...</title>
            <author>Ollyffe, John, 1647-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O286</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13724683</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13724683</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 846:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessedness of good men after death a sermon preach'd at the funeral of the Revd. Mr. Henry Cornish, B.D., who died on Sunday, Decemb. 18th, in the eighty ninth year of his age and was interred on Thursday, Decemb. 22d, 1698, in the Church of Bisiter, in the County of Oxford : with a preface to rectifie some misrepresentations &amp;c. in a late pamphlet, entitled Some remarks on the life, death, and burial of the said Mr. Cornish / by John Ollyffe ...</title>
                  <author>Ollyffe, John, 1647-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cornish, Henry, d. 1698.</term>
               <term>Kennett, White, 1660-1728. --  Some remarks on the life, death, and burial of Mr. Henry Cornish.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XIV, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101574:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Bleſſedneſs of Good Men-after Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the FUNERAL OF THE Rev<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> Mr. <hi>Henry Corniſh,</hi> B. D.</p>
            <p>Who died on <hi>Sunday, Decemb.</hi> 18th, in the Eighty Ninth Year of his Age, and was Interred on <hi>Thurſday, Decemb.</hi> 22d, 1698. in the Church of <hi>Biſiter,</hi> in the County of <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a Preface to Rectifie ſome Miſrepreſentations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in a late Pamphlet, Entitled, <hi>Some Remarks on the Life, Death and Burial of the ſaid Mr.</hi> Corniſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Ollyffe, <hi>Rector of</hi> Dunton, <hi>in the County of</hi> Bucks.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:101574:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101574:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>I Had not the leaſt Intent, when I firſt Compoſed, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Preach'd this Sermon, to make it Publick. But there being a very buſie and angry Reflector, who it ſeems was then an Auditor, who hath concern'd himſelf to Print Remarks upon it in a very little time after it was Preach'd, which I cannot but take for very diſ-ingenious and hard Uſage; and not knowing what may be the Conſequence thereof, among thoſe who may frame their Judgments only by his Report, and may be apt to kindle at his Fire: I think my ſelf obliged for my own Vindication, as alſo to ſatisfie the Deſires of ſome, whom, I have a Reſpect for, at length to ſend it abroad, and to take ſome little Notice of his Reflections upon it. And I am not without hope, but that by the Bleſſing of God it may be of uſe to ſome devout Minds at leaſt, howſoever He, or ſome Others took it.</p>
            <p>This Reflector ſaith, <hi>He is really as much againſt a Perſecuting Spirit, as any of thoſe Men, whoſe Intereſt or Coldneſs it is to be, for what they call Moderation.</hi> He knoweth himſelf beſt. Far be it therefore from me to charge him with that, which he denieth of himſelf. But it ſeems, tho he be againſt Perſecution, yet he is not for Moderation: For this he reckons to be from <hi>Coldneſs</hi> or <hi>Intereſt;</hi> which are too low Principles for him to be influenc'd by. And ſo one would think by him. Now I muſt own to this Reflector, and to all the World, that I am not only againſt a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Spirit, and ſo have always been, but am for Moderation too; yet not from <hi>Intereſt</hi> or <hi>Coldneſs,</hi> but becauſe I think it is a very great Chriſtian Vertue. And I believe, if the Reflector had ſomething leſs of a Perſecuting Spirit, and a little of Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, it would be never the worſe; and then I am apt to think, he had ſpared theſe Reflections.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, <hi>He is as much by Temper and by Conſcience againſt Railing and Rudeneſs, as againſt Fawning and Flattery.</hi> 'Tis
<pb facs="tcp:101574:3"/>
great pity, that a good Temper ſhould ever be ſpoiled by bad Cuſtoms; or that Paſſion or Heat ſhou'd ever over-rule ſuch a Principle, as Conſcience. But yet, ſo we ſee it comes to paſs ſometimes. <hi>He would have all Juſtice and Charity,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>ſhewed to the Dead of all Perſwaſions.</hi> And I perceive, he is willing enough, that Diſſenters ſhould have as much Reſpect ſhewn them that way, as other <hi>Men of the moſt deſperate Sects and Factions,</hi> as <hi>Phariſees,</hi> or as the <hi>moſt deplorable Hereticks in the Chriſtian Church.</hi> Becauſe there may be <hi>ſome laudable Qualities even in ſuch Men; and they are not ſo loſt to God and Goodneſs, but they ſay and do ſome things that are Praiſe worthy, and of good Report,</hi> which is a very notable Conceſſion, and which the Diſſenters no doubt will Con him much Thanks for, that they may be treated at leaſt as well as <hi>Turks, Infidels, Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He is not angry,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>That this Grave Ancient Man was publickly treated with ſo much Reſpect and Honour;</hi> and how comes it to paſs then, that he is ſo angry with me for treating him with this Reſpect and Honour which I have done? Eſpecially when he grants, that Funeral Sermons ſhould be interpreted with Candour and Conceſſion.</p>
            <p>But <hi>it raiſed his Indignation,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>to hear ſuch an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue upon a profeſs'd maintainer of Diviſion and Schiſm.</hi> What that Harangue was, is to be ſeen in the Sermon, towards the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter End, which is there without the leaſt omiſſion or alteration of any one Word, that I know of; which, if he had conſider'd better, and had not done in haſte what he did, he might have thought, that there had been no ſuch occaſion given for this loud Out-cry, which he hath made in this Buſineſs.</p>
            <p>As to much of what I have mention'd in the Character of this Worthy Perſon, this Reflector hath ſaid as much as I, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more, as I ſhall give an account afterwards, being better acquainted with ſome Paſſages of his Life of late, than I was; and if it be more to the purpoſe too, I am very glad of it, and thank him for it. But for <hi>thoſe Strokes of his Life and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, which,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>ſome People had objected, as Blots and Blemiſhes to him, and which I ſhould have made an Ingenious Apology for,</hi> I knew none there, that had made ſuch Objections, or that expected ſuch Apologies. And I did not in the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign then, that my Sermon ſhould have gone farther. The Reflector now being well acquainted with <hi>Panegyrick,</hi> hath ſhewed me,
<pb facs="tcp:101574:3"/>
what he thinks I might have ſaid both ways; but hath inſerted or added withal very ſlighting and undervaluing Reflections, which I, who have leſs Skill that way, cannot but think he ought to have let alone; and no doubt he had done ſo, if he had deſigned his Remarks in real kindneſs to his Memory. But I for my part did not think, I had need to concern my ſelf with any thing of that Nature; but muſt be of Opinion ſtill after all, that he hath ſaid, That it would have been plainly abſurd in the preſent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; and that much alſo of what he has ſaid, hath neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh of Decency nor good Nature in it; and therefore I choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to expreſs in few Words what I knew in the time of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with him, and to omit all other Things which did not concern me: For it was not my Buſineſs to give an Hiſtory of his Life, nor indeed could I do it, being but little acquainted with it, but only in ſhort to expreſs his Character, as far as I knew. And if I did deliver this <hi>with as much noiſe and aſſurance, as Lungs and Liberty could take,</hi> which He being an Auditor, ſaith, I did; I hope it may well be aſcribed to my Affection and Senſe of Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which this Reflector grants in Funeral Orations there ſhould be an Allowance for. But that <hi>I ſpake it in Triumph over the Head of the Parochial Miniſter,</hi> as this Reflector alſo by a moſt uncharitable Cenſure layeth to my Charge, I abhor and deteſt it with as much Indignation, as he ſaith, he heard it. Far be it from me ever to have had ſuch an Intent or Thought, which I am ſure never was in my Heart; nor could there be the leaſt colour for ſuch a Cenſure, but my Affectionate Delivery; which the Occaſion drew from me.</p>
            <p>But the great Quarrel againſt me, I perceive is, That I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him ſo much for his Piety and Holineſs, which this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector calls <hi>Sainting of him as it were;</hi> and that <hi>I pronounc'd him Bleſſed,</hi> that is, I expreſs'd my Belief of the Bleſſedneſs of the Man, <hi>Who,</hi> this Reflector ſaith, <hi>had been the Voice and the Soul of the Schiſm in that Town;</hi> that is, had been a Preacher to a ſeparate Congregation there. In which Station of his yet, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by what this Reflector himſelf afterwards ſaith of him, He managed himſelf with very great Modeſty and Inoffenſiveneſs. And this Reflector himſelf alſo pronounceth him an <hi>Honeſt Man;</hi> that being the Appellation which he giveth him. And if he was ſuch an One, then whatever his Failures or Miſtakes had been in ſome Points, either of Opinion or Practice; and ſuppoſe this for One, which this Reflector mentions, yet he muſt needs believe,
<pb facs="tcp:101574:4"/>
that theſe Failures and Miſtakes were Unwilling and Involuntary in him. And ſure He cannot but hold, but that a very eminent degree of Piety may be very well conſiſtent with more than one involuntary Failures and Miſtakes. And a Man may be a very Good Man, tho' in ſome Things He be in the wrong. And if I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved him Pious, as I verily did, I can ſee no Reaſon, but that I might at that time openly expreſs my Belief thereof. And then ſure I ought to believe him Bleſſed too, if I ought to believe Pious Men to be Bleſſed. And then why might not I expreſs my Belief thereof likewiſe?</p>
            <p>But, he ſaith, <hi>I ſhould have conſider'd the Place, wherein I ſtood upon Courteſie and Sufferance, and ſhould in good Manners have ſaid nothing offenſive to the Perſon, by whoſe Leave I came there;</hi> I verily thought, I had done ſo, as he ſaith, I ſhould have done. I commended him for his Goodneſs, Humility and Piety; and I think, he deſerved it. And I could never imagine, That the Commendation of the Piety of any Man, who did deſerve that Commendation, could be offenſive to him, or any other worthy Perſon.</p>
            <p>But it ſeems I ſpoke, as if I <hi>had his Perſon in Admiration, and taught thoſe preſent to have it ſo.</hi> And what then? It was for that, which was Good and Excellent in him; and what harm could there be in that? That ſure could never, as this Reflector adds, <hi>ſeal up the Obſtinate, or confirm them in the Error of their Ways,</hi> when I did not commend him for any Error, but for that which was Good in him. Nor can it be a <hi>delivering up of the Church,</hi> which I hope is as much for Holineſs in all Men, as I, or any other Perſon can be. Nor can the Commendation of a Perſon's Piety and Goodneſs, tho' in ſome Things differing from me, and from the Church of which I am a Member, be to <hi>countenance Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and Diviſions, to daub with untempered Morter, or to propheſie Deceits;</hi> all which are the judicious and kind Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks, which this Reflector makes upon my Performance. What! Cannot a Man commend a Diſſenter, but that muſt be to commend his Diſſent? And if I did not commend his Diſſent, how was that to countenance Diviſions? And if I commended him for that Good, which was really in Him, I ſpake the Truth, however this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector would inſinuate the contrary, and if a Man ſpeaks Truth, is that <hi>to Propheſie Deceits?</hi> I am no Diſſenter, but I love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Diſſenters that are good Men, for their Goodneſs ſake, tho' not for their Diſſent; and ſo I ought to do. To ſpeak plainly,
<pb facs="tcp:101574:4"/>
I believe the Conſtitution of our Church to be Juſtifiable, and in the main Primitive; and the Terms of our Church Communion to be Lawful; or elſe I ſhould Lie to God and Men in what I have done in Conformity; which God forbid; or now muſt renounce it, which I ſee no Reaſon for. And therefore I know, I ought not to do any thing, that I think might tend to alienate or withdraw any Perſon from it; nor did I ever intend any ſuch thing in the whole Courſe of my Life, but to ſweeten Men's Spirits, and to reconcile them to it, as much I could. But I ſee many Perſons have invincible Prejudices againſt ſome Things, which the Church of which I am, as well as my ſelf, think Indifferent. And if this Reflector thinks, they cannot be Good Men becauſe of ſuch Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, and certain Practices of theirs following thereupon, I am of another Opinion. For I believe, there have been, and are a great many ſuch notwithſtanding; and as ſuch I am bound to Love and Honour them, and not only to exchange with them the common <hi>Offices of Humanity,</hi> which is all, that this Reflector ſeems to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Tho' 'tis their Goodneſs, and not their Prejudices or Diſſent, that I Love and Honour in them. And on the other ſide, to ſpeak as plainly, If any be Bad Men, let them be of the Church never ſo much; if they can pray and ſwear almoſt in a Breath; if they are drunk with Wine or ſtrong Drink, tho' not with Opinions; if they hate Faction, and nothing elſe beſides; if they have a Zeal for Forms and outward Obſervances, and there it reſts, I ſhall never have much reſpect for ſuch Puppits and Apes in Religion, that have nothing at all of the Life and Spirit of it.</p>
            <p>I have indeed theſe Expreſſions in the Character of this Good Man, <hi>That his Labour in that way, wherein he thought he might Glorifie God, even to extream Old Age</hi> (for now he was in the Eighty Ninth Year of it) <hi>was an Inſtance of his great delight therein, of his Pious Zeal for the promoting of Religion, and of his Earneſt Deſire of the Eternal Welfare of Men.</hi> I did not ſpeak this to juſtifie his Way in the Circumſtances of it, but to commend his Holy Intention and Zeal for the promoting of Piety in it, which I thought his long-continued Labour was a great Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of. For ſo I perſwade my ſelf, it was intended by him, and that the matter and end of his Service and Performances, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Human Frailties, were for the glorifying of God, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of true Religion, and not of Diſorders and Diviſions. For this Reflector himſelf obſerves enough to clear him in that Matter, if his Preaching was like the reſt of his Converſation. For he
<pb facs="tcp:101574:5"/>
himſelf obſerveth, <hi>That notwithſtanding many Diſadvantages of Education and Intereſt; which he lay under, that he was no Bigot, no violent angry Man; That he had really a Meekneſs of Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which kept him from Wranglings and Diſputes; That he had a goodneſs of Nature, which inclined him to a fair Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence with ſome Church-Divines; and that it ſeemed his peculiar frame of Spirit, to be reſerved and inoffenſive; That like a Wiſe and Good Man he took only the defenſive part in thoſe ſhort Diſcourſes, that had been held with him; That he never in his hearing railed at, or run down the Conſtitution of the Church; but pleaded calmly for Moderation and Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and bearing with one another. And that he often choſe to make as it were ſome Apology for keeping up a ſeparate Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in oppoſition to the Church; and would ſay, he was brought thither by the invitation and importunity of ſuch; as were good People. And that it was not his Intention to keep them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Church, but ſhould ſometimes ſet them an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of going thither himſelf. And that he did at firſt reſolve to begin and end his Publick Exerciſes at ſuch Hours, as ſhould not interfere wirh the Solemn Service of the Church, but diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs them from one place to attend at the other. And that he ſeemed to deſire no better Character, than what had been freely given to his Predeceſſor Mr.</hi> Troughton (<hi>by one, who,</hi> as this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector ſaith, <hi>had not the Cuſtom to flatter that Party) who was very moderate,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And that he ſeemed to value himſelf on this Happineſs, that he had received Holy Orders from a Biſhop of the Church of</hi> England. <hi>That he Married one of his Daughters to a Conforming Divine, and uſed his Intereſt to poſſeſs him of a better Benefice, under the Condition of Subſcription and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, which the Law required.</hi> Concerning which Relations, and others which he adds, I know nothing, except that barely of the Marriage of his Daughter, and therefore could ſay nothing of them. But I think even from this Reflector's account of him, I have Reaſon alſo to conclude, That this Good Man's Pains and Zeal were intended by him, not for the promoting of Diviſions and Diſorders, but of the Service of God, and of true Piety and Holineſs; which was what I aimed at, in that which I ſaid of him in that part of his Character. Therefore to conclude this, I cannot yet be perſwaded, but that what I ſaid of this Worthy Man, was downright Juſtice to his Memory, and not <hi>Fawning or Flattery,</hi> as this Reflector would inſinuate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:101574:5"/>But there is another Thing it ſeems, that raiſed the Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Reflector, <hi>viz. That in all my Diſcourſe there was not a word of Exhortation to Unity and Peace, nor ſo much as wiſhing thoſe People to come more frequently to that Holy Place, where they were now Aſſembled, and where their Beloved Teacher choſe to lie at Reſt: That there was nothing,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>but an Applauſe of the Perſon, and then a ſilent Conſent to the Merits of the Cauſe.</hi> And thereupon he inſinuates, <hi>as if I made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity and Separation indifferent Things; as if I was an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for Indifference in Communion; and had cowardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed that Altar, to the Service whereof I had been legally Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</hi> For my part, I cannot but wonder at this Reflector's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and by what Logick he could ever infer, That the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe and Commendation of a Perſon for his Goodneſs, and Zeal for the promoting of Piety, which was all that I deſigned; and my omitting of that, which did not concern me at that time, could be a ſilent Conſent to the Merits of a Cauſe; or that it was to be an Advocate for indifference in Communion, to ſay nothing at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it. But a little Wit, and a great deal of ill Nature, by the help of ſpightful <hi>Innuendo</hi>'s will be able to infer any thing from any thing. But I muſt tell this Reflector, That that was no part of my Buſineſs at that time, which he expected of me. My Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was to Preach a Funeral Sermon at the Interment of an Old and Good Friend, from whom I had received formerly many Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; to which I was called by the Friends of the Deceaſed, and for the doing of which they had obtained leave of the Miniſter of the Town. In this Sermon I did endeavour plainly and famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly (which it ſeems was a Fault with ſome) to repreſent ſome Things, which might be for the Conſolation of Good People againſt the fears of Death, and to exhort and encourage others to eſpouſe Religion, which had ſo great Advantages attending upon it. And this I think, by this Reflector's leave, was a proper Subject for ſuch an Occaſion. And this Subject I having choſen, this I was to purſue. But yet could not omit ſaying ſomething, tho' it was but a little (and I think, if I committed any Fault, it was in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too little) out of Gratitude and hearty Reſpect to the Memory of my Reverend and good Friend Departed. But I could not think it any part of my Buſineſs upon that Occaſion, to inſiſt upon the Points of Unity and Schiſm: Let my Thoughts or Opinion about them have been what they would, or tho' they were never ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:101574:6"/>
ſuch as this Reflector would have them; therefore I think the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector blames me without Cauſe, as guilty of a grand Omiſſion of that, which was nothing to the purpoſe of what I was then about; but it ſeems to me, would have been a downright Soleciſm at a Funeral Solemnity. And I have never obſerved, That Excurſions of this Nature have ever had any good Effect, but directly the contrary.</p>
            <p>Yet I can aſſure this Reflector, and do profeſs to him, That I have as much deſired and longed for the Peace of the Church, its Security and Eſtabliſhment, and the Union of Diſſenters to it; that all our Animoſities might be compoſed, our Breaches healed, and our Differences happily brought to an end, as ever any hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Man did long for his Meat and Drink, and would be glad to promote it by all proper Means. I am ſure it is for the intereſt of Religion, for the advancement of the Name and Honour of our great Lord and Maſter, to have the Church of God at Unity with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelf. It is that, which would make the Church it ſelf Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and Venerable, and formidable to all its Enemies; or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it will be the way to have no Enemies at all, when they ſhall ſee the happy Effects of the Chriſtian Doctrine upon the Lives and Spirits of Men, and Love, Charity and good Will planted and fructifying in the Chriſtian World. I am very ſure from the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>That the whole Body fitly joined together, and compacted by that, which every Joint ſupplieth, according to the effectual working in the Meaſure of every part, maketh encreaſe of the Body, unto the edifying of it ſelf in Love,</hi> Eph. <hi>4.16.</hi> And therefore all that could be done, ſhould be done, towards the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of this mutual Love, and the ſettling of Concord among all the Members of this Body. All proper Means ſhould be made uſe of, all Methods taken; any way, any expedient tried that can be; unneceſſary occaſions of Contention ſhould be removed, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions made, and yielding on all ſides; and if one Thing will not do then another, and another ſhould be tried, like Phyſick in a difficult Caſe: And it would be all worth the while, for the promoting of Chriſtian Love and Charity, which is ſo great a part of Religion, and which is ſo helpful to all the reſt. And 'tis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that we muſt aim at, and which all Things whatſoever ſhould ſubſerve to. Order, Government, Diſcipline, Ordinances, Miniſters, and Miniſtry, are all but to promote Religion, Faith,
<pb facs="tcp:101574:6"/>
Purity, and Charity among Men. And 'tis Pride, Intereſt, Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Stiffneſs, and Revenge, that ſpoil and hinder all. But whoſoever they are, that do not prefer Religion and Peace above every Thing elſe, all violent Incendiaries, all Self-ſeekers, all Carnal Politicians, that to gratifie an Humour, to ſerve an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, or to keep up a Ballance, make it their Buſineſs to foment Diſcord, and to keep Diviſions a-foot, I will be bold to ſay, they know not what manner of Spirit they are of, they ſeek not Chriſt but themſelves, their God is their Belly, and their Glory is in their Shame. And let them be Diſſenters, or Church-Men, or of what Denomination they will, they are not true Chriſtians. <hi>This Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom deſcendeth not from above, but is Earthly, Senſual, Deviliſh. For where Envying and Strife is, there is Confuſion and every E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Work. But the Wiſdom, that is from above, is firſt pure, then peacable, gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, without Partiality, and without Hypocriſie. And the fruit of Righteouſneſs is ſown in Peace of them that make Peace,</hi> Jam. <hi>3.15.</hi> This Peace I am for. I love neither Faction nor Fury, Obſtinacy nor Revenge; but could be glad to do any thing in the World, to convince, heal, or reconcile. And ſo I hope would ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others. But I can ſee but little ſucceſs of Attempts that have been made this way; and can have but little hopes, till God is pleaſed to take the Matter into his own Hands, to bring the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Men to a certain Temper on all ſides, which yet the moſt do not ſeem to be inclined to; which hath been no ſmall Trouble to me to obſerve, ſo that I have been almoſt tired out with vain Expectation in this Matter. But if I can do no good towards a Compoſure or Accommodation of theſe our Uncharitable and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Differences, I am reſolved however I will not irritate or inflame, what I would be glad to heal; as I dare ſay, I ſhould have done, if I had taken this Reflector's Meaſures.</p>
            <p>But now we are upon it, let us conſider, what Methods He would have had me uſed to bring thoſe People to Church more frequently at other times. Firſt, he ſaith, <hi>I ſhould have taken the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to Commemorate the great Charity of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>which like a Natural and Indulgent Mother, hath always open Arms to receive even her Froward and Rebellious Sons; and alloweth her Offices of Chriſtian Burial to thoſe, who deſpiſe her other Ordinances, that ſhe patiently waits their Submiſſion, while
<pb facs="tcp:101574:7"/>
they live, and affords them the laſt Offices of Piety, when they come to Die; which ſure might win upon all Ingenious Spirits to oblige her with Conformity and Obedience in all reaſonable Service.</hi> But I am apt to be of Opinion after all, that they would hardly have thought this Argument to have any great Weight in it. Charity is a very good and obliging Thing. But unleſs they can have Satisfaction given them about the Reaſonableneſs and Unexcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionableneſs of the Service it ſelf, which they Diſſent from, which this Reflector doth not proceed to, nor doth adviſe me to it, tho' that was the chief Thing, and would have been moſt to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; I doubt the Churches Charity alone, in the reſpect which he mentions, would hardly bring them to Conformity and Obedience to it.</p>
            <p>But to give Him his due: He doth not inſiſt upon this, as the chief Thing, being apprehenſive, 'tis likely, of the weakneſs of it taken by it ſelf. It was ſomething elſe he had principally in his Thoughts, as appears by his long Harangue about it, which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but wonder at, <hi>viz. That it was an Holy Place where they were now Aſſembled, and where their Beloved Teacher choſe to lie at Reſt,</hi> which He had hinted before. And that I might have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, <hi>That they do not Die ſo much out of Charity with the Church, as is commonly imputed to them.</hi> For they like well enough to be Buried there, in the Church Ground. <hi>And when they come to depart out of this World, they leave their Bodies as a Legacy to it. And to leave a Legacy to one, is juſtly thought a Sign and Seal of Reconciliation and perfect Love.</hi> I never heard indeed that they were much out of conceit with the Earth of the Church-Floor. And if that be a ſign of their Reconciliation to the Church, I find they are contented to give a Teſtimony of it at any time, when there is the like Occaſion. <hi>And tho' theſe Brethren chuſe to ſerve God in a Common and Unhallowed Barn, rather than in a Place Solemnly Devoted to be God's Houſe of Prayer; yet on Death-Bed Thoughts they cannot Will their Bodies to be committed to the Threſhing-Floor; but make it their laſt Option to be Buried with their Forefathers,</hi> as it is Natural, or Cuſtomary for all to deſire; <hi>and let their Sepulchres at leaſt be on the good old Conſecrated Ground;</hi> tho' I dare ſay, they never think of the Conſecration, when they do ſo. <hi>And who knoweth, but the Better Sort of Diſſenters may have ſuch Scruples on them as theſe? That
<pb facs="tcp:101574:7"/>
if they ſhould be too ſoon admitted into the Boſom of the Church, they could by no means live up to the Rules and Orders of it; whereas delaying their Admiſſion to the laſt,</hi> when their Bodies are brought to Church, <hi>They may poſſibly ſuppoſe, that ſuch a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Action may determine their Salvation; and to be Buried in the Church be a ſufficient Atonement for their long Abſence from it.</hi> And then upon this he ſaith, <hi>I might have took occaſion to perſwade the Brethren there preſent, that they would be as well affected in their Life and Health, as they generally come to be in their laſt Sickneſs and point of Death; that is, to bring their Bodies to the Chuich, whilſt their Souls are yet in them; which would be a more acceptable Sacrifice, than the bare Carcaſe and Refuſe of Mortality. And, why ſhould they deſire to be Interred within the Precincts of the Church; unleſs they think it their own laſt Home and proper Place? Would any of us requeſt, that our Dead Bodies ſhould be carried into an Enemies Country, rather than be laid up in our Native Land? It muſt argue ſome good Affection ſure to the Spot of Earth, where we reſolve to lay down our Mortal Man, and to mix our common Duſt.</hi> And moreover therefore, <hi>I ſhould have encouraged theſe Brethren, not to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Aſſembling of themſelves together in that Holy Place, where the Mournful Occaſion had now brought them. The Ground was not Polluted with Idolatrous Worſhip; if it had, their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Teacher would not have deſired to have found there an Ark of Reſt for his Earthly Tabernacle.</hi> By theſe extraordinary Arguments and Motives, I ſhould very powerfully have Exhorted the Brethren there preſent, to come to Church every <hi>Sunday</hi> in the Year. And if any of them ſhould have an Humour more Obſtinate than ordinary, ſuch rare and ſingular Reaſon and Rhetorick toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, muſt needs have knock'd it down in an inſtant.</p>
            <p>Now I muſt own to this Reflector, That theſe wiſe Thoughts ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came into my Head, and if they had, I ſhould certainly have ſent them packing, as ſoon as I had obſerved them. For I ſhould certainly have diſdained to have trifled in this manner. Theſe Topicks might ſerve the turn for a young Declaimer, of whom, if he can but ſhew a little Wit, it is not expected, that he ſhould talk much Reaſon. But doth this Reflector think, that to talk of Holy Places, and Holy Conſecrated Ground, and of the contrary, Prophaneneſs of a Common and Unhallowed Barn, and the Threſhing-Floor,
<pb facs="tcp:101574:8"/>
would be of ſuch mighty force to bring Diſſenters to Church? Would not this rather have offended, than perſwaded them? Doth not he know, they have but little Opinion of ſuch Holineſs and Conſecration? And yet that they chuſe to Worſhip on the Threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Floor, not becauſe they think it beſt, but for want of a more convenient Place? And becauſe they are willing to have their Dead Carcaſes, that are without Sence or Feeling, brought to be Buried in the Church Ground among their Forefathers, which they think is a convenient Repoſitory for them, doth he think that this would do the mighty Feat to perſwade them to bring their Living Souls to Church to Worſhip there, when they think, they can do better elſewhere? Doth not be know, that 'tis the Service that they take Exception againſt, and not the Walls, or Seats, or Ground, or Earth? And it is impoſſible, that He ſhould trifle ſo, as to imagine, that the Better Sort of Diſſenters ſhould think, that if they ſhould be too ſoon admitted into the Boſom of the Church, they could by no means live up to the Rules of it? Doth he think, that they take the Rules of our Church to be ſtricter than thoſe of their own? Or that they ſhould think, that their chuſing to be Buried at laſt in the Church Ground would Atone for their long Abſence from the Church Service, and that this being their final Action would determine their Salvation? Would not they take this to be a downright Affront to them, that we ſhould take them to be ſuch ſilly Creatures? Of all Men living, if I were to Diſcourſe of this Matter, I would not come to this Reflector to ſuggeſt Heads or Arguments to me for it. Certainly it is a thouſand times better, quite to hold one's Peace, than to talk thus quite croſs to the Buſineſs. Theſe are rare and ſingular Thoughts, and I dare ſay are none-ſuch of their kind; and this laſt eſpecially He took for a notable piece of Wit and Ingenuity, it being no doubt his own moſt genuine Off-ſpring; and was ſo taken with the miſ-ſhapen Fancy, that he could not chuſe but make much of it, and then by all means muſt produce it to open View, that all may admire it. But a little Charity, and Judgment withal, which this Reflector hath taken great care not to betray too much of, had moſt certainly <hi>finally determined</hi> it out of the way.</p>
            <p>Now at laſt, He adds, That <hi>the Ceremonies are few, and inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive; the Prayers are Devout, and pathetically Good; the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb facs="tcp:101574:8"/>
are Practical and Plain.</hi> I know nothing, that this Reflector hath ſaid to the purpoſe, but only this. But if he had alſo a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle farther ſet out the inoffenſiveneſs of the Ceremonies, the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Prayers, and the uſefulneſs of the Sermons, it would have been no doubt ſo much the more effectual. But it looks, as if he leaſt deſcended upon this, He ſlights it over ſo quick. For this Reflector is only for Rare, Antique, and Unuſual Things; a little plain honeſt Truth is not ſo agreeable to his roving, and high-ſoaring Fancy. Doth he think, that ſuch general Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only would have been ſo powerful to perſwade? Or that his, or my telling them ſo, which perhaps they have heard an hundred times over, would upon a ſudden convince and alter their Minds, and change their reliſh of Things? If I had been to Diſcourſe of this Matter, I think I ought to have gone a little deeper into the Controverſie, taken it to pieces, and unravelled its Parts, to break the force of Objections. But was that a Time or Seaſon for all this? Would not that have been a pretty undertaking at a Funeral? Beſides, there are many Books writ about theſe Things; and many and long Diſputes Printed about them. And if theſe do not prevail, I don't believe, that the ſlight Flurts of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flector's Rhetorick, or the moſt that I could ſay, will ever do it. For I have no ſuch mighty conceit of my Abilities that way, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this Reflector hath of his: We have Diſputed long enough. And we know the time, when ſome Severities have been uſed too. And yet we ſee, that all hath had but little Effect. I think there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we were all better yield, what we can, and ſhake Hands, and Love one another.</p>
            <p>I have now ſaid, what I intend to ſay in this Matter. If the Reflector be not ſatisfied herewith, it will be in vain for me any farther to attempt his Satisfaction. I ſhall not preſume to give him any Advice, but let him alone to take his own Meaſures. Yet I ſhall not refuſe any from him, provided he be happier in adviſing another time, than in what he hath done already. But if He intends to Diſpute or Criminate on, I ſhall leave him to enjoy himſelf in his own Humour, but I intend to give my ſelf no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trouble about it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, 'tis a great comfort to think of that State and Place, where all Imperfection ſhall be done away, and where all
<pb facs="tcp:101574:9"/>
Differences and Contentions ſhall be at an end; where I hope yet to meet this now angry Brother; and do moſt heartily pray, that both He, and I, and whoſoever hath any Ill will to me in this World, may by the free Grace of God pardoning our Sins, and accepting us in Chriſt Jeſus, be at laſt received into the Embraces of our Bleſſed Lord, and may Live and Joy together in the moſt ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fruition of his everlaſting Love. And in the mean time, if to Preach up the Doctrines of our Holy Religion, with Zeal, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Earneſtneſs, in order to the preparing of Men for this, be Cant, Noiſe, and Aſſurance, I beſeech the God of Heaven to give me more of it. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THE Author hath alſo Publiſhed a Thankſgiving Sermon for the Delivery of this Kingdom from Popery and Arbitrary Power.</p>
            <p>A Brief Defence of Infant-Baptiſm with an Appendix, wherein is ſhewed, That it is not neceſſary that Baptiſm ſhould be Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred by Dipping.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter's Laſt-Advice to his People, being a Farewel Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached at <hi>Almer</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> at the Author's leaving the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101574:9"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rev. 14 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>I heard a Voice from Heaven, ſaying unto me, Write, Bleſſed are the Dead, which Die in the Lord, from henceforth, yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN theſe Words we have Three Things conſiderable, which we have an account of, from the Voice and Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they, who <hi>Die in the Lord,</hi> are Bleſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Reaſon or Parts of this Bleſſedneſs: <hi>They reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The time of the Beginning, or Commencement of this Bleſſedneſs. <hi>From henceforth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, They that Die in the Lord, are Bleſſed.</hi> But here the Queſtion is, who they are, that may be ſaid to <hi>Die in the Lord?</hi> Or what it is, that is intended in that Expreſſion or Deſcription of thoſe, to whom the Bleſſing here doth belong.</p>
            <p>I make no doubt, as it is alſo generally underſtood, that theſe Words were eſpecially and principally intended for the comfort of ſuch Chriſtians, who were then like to ſuffer in thoſe Days of Perſecution of the Church of God; whereby <hi>the Patience of the Saints,</hi> of which he ſpeaks, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. was ſo much Exerciſed. The outward State of the Church was then very diſmal and ſad, in thoſe dark and afflictive Times. And therefore it was but need to give a Word of Comfort and Support to ſuch, as were like to bear the Burden of thoſe direful Calamities, that were about to fall upon them. This ſeems to be mainly intended here in this Bleſſing, that they might be encouraged thereby to hold out in their Faith and Profeſſion, notwithſtanding all that ſhould fall upon them.</p>
            <p>In this Senſe then, by thoſe that <hi>Die in the Lord,</hi> the Holy Martyrs muſt firſt be intended, who laid down their Lives <hi>for the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101574:10"/>
Lord,</hi> that is, for his ſake, or for their Adherence to his Faith and Goſpel. This being a very grievous Caſe, God was pleaſed often in the Scriptures to provide for their Encouragement.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>It is a faithful ſaying,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>if we be Dead with him, we ſhall alſo Live with him: If we Suffer, we ſhall alſo Reign with him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16, 17.</note> And <hi>that we ſhall be alſo glorified together;</hi> and <hi>that the Sufferings of this preſent time, are not worthy to be compared with the Glory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>that ſhall be revealed in us.</hi> For, ſaith he, <hi>our light Affliction, which is but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>Seeing it is a Righteous Thing with God, to recompence Tribulation to them that trouble you; and to you, who are troubled, reſt with us, when the Lord Jeſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven, when he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and admired in all them, that believe.</hi> And a great many more ſuch Promiſes and Encouragements there are to Suffering Chriſtians, who Die in the Lord.</p>
            <p>But then it muſt be likewiſe ſuppoſed, That thoſe, who Die thus <hi>in, or for the Lord,</hi> and for their Adherence to the Faith of Chriſt, do Die in, or under the ſanctifying Power of that Faith alſo; the great Deſign of which was to <hi>Purifie the Heart, and Work by Love.</hi> Without which Effect obtained, Martyrdom it ſelf, if it could be ſuppoſed, would not at all profit them; as we have the Apoſtle's own Reſolution in the Caſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3. For, ſaith He, <hi>Tho' I give my Body to be burnt, and have not Charity,</hi> which is the great Chriſtian Vertue, and comprehenſive of all the reſt, <hi>it profiteth me nothing.</hi> For the great End of the Faith of Chriſt, and of the belief of the Goſpel, is to make Men Holy, to recover the Image of God in Men, that they may Live to his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. So that there is no Salvation without this, let Men's Sufferings for the Faith ſeem to have been never ſo great.</p>
            <p>But then on the other ſide, they who Live and Die in the Power of that Faith, having felt the transforming and ſanctifying Vertue thereof, and ſo have attain'd to the great End of it, tho' they have not undergone the Sufferings of Martyrdom, ſurely may be ſaid <hi>to Die in the Lord</hi> alſo. They Die United to him, adhering to his Intereſt and Cauſe. Yea, they <hi>Die for him,</hi> fighting under his Banner, and in his Quarrel, againſt all his Enemies, the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil. And theſe are alſo <hi>Martyres Animo,</hi> in the Diſpoſition of their Minds, and they would by his Grace maintain the Field, for his Sake, to the very Death. And the ſufferings of Mortification, which they have endured already,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101574:10"/>
are a kind of Martyrdom, in cutting off their Right Hands, and plucking out their Right Eyes, in bringing down the Old Man, and crucifying the whole Body of Sin: Therefore there is no doubt, but that to theſe alſo the Bleſſing here mentioned doth belong. For theſe, the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>being made free from Sin, and become Servants to God, have their Fruit unto Holineſs, and the end everlaſting Life,</hi> Rom. 6.22. And all theſe ſhall partake of the Inheritance, <hi>which are ſanctified by Faith, that is in Chriſt,</hi> Acts 26.18. In which Senſe 'tis a very comfortable Conſideration to all truly Penitent and Sound Believers, and Good Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>For the evidencing of which, theſe few Things may be farther conſidered, to perſwade us, that it ſhall be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe the Spirit of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt is in them, ſo that they are <hi>led by the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>live in the Spirit,</hi> by the Dictates, and according to the Rules of the Holy Spirit of God. <hi>Now there is no Condemnation,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>to them that are in Chriſt Jeſus, that walk not after the Fleſh, but after the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. For the Law of the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus hath made them free from the Law of Sin and Death,</hi> Rom. 8.1.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>And if the Spirit of him, that raiſed up Jeſus from the Dead dwell in you, he that raiſed up Chriſt from the Dead ſhall alſo quicken your Mortal Bodies by his Spirit that dwelleth in you.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>For as many as are led by the Spirit of God, they are the Sons of God; and if Children, then Heirs, Heirs of God, and Joint Heirs with Chriſt.</hi> Theſe Men are the <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and God will no more deſtroy thoſe Temples, than he will allow others to do ſo. But the Spirit of God, with the Bleſſed Fruits of it, which is in them when they Die, is a ſure Pledge and Earneſt of more Bleſſings to be received afterwards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> From hence it will follow, That the Image of God is upon them, and that in a more eminent manner, than it is upon any others. They being renewed <hi>after the Image of him that Created them, in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs.</hi> So that they have not only the Natural Image of God, as it may be called for diſtinction ſake, in the Spirituality, Powers, and Immortality of their Spirits; but they have the Moral Image of God alſo, which is the Glory of the Divine Nature; which is wrought in them by the transforming Power of the Holy Ghoſt, to whoſe Holy Dictates and Motions they have been brought to ſubmit themſelves. And by this Means they are according to their Meaſure made like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. And thereby it muſt needs be, That God's Love of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101574:11"/>
muſt be towards them, and his Delight muſt be in them. For however there may be ſome Blots in this Image in them, yet theſe being not ſuch, as to ſpoil the Beauty thereof, God will have a favourable Reſpect unto them; and they may depend upon it, that He will not caſt them off.</p>
            <p>Theſe Men are not of a Temper, or Spirit, for Devils, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernal Spirits, to dwell with them. For they do oppoſe their Dark Kingdom, and are grieved at the Converſation of the Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by whom it is promoted. And therefore they may be ſure, they ſhall never be put to Herd with them in the Infernal Lake hereafter. But the time will come, when all ſhall be carried to their Like; tho' it cannot be done here, where the Tares and the Wheat muſt be ſuffered to grow together. But at laſt the Sheep ſhall be put by <hi>themſelves,</hi> and the Goats by <hi>themſelves;</hi> all Wicked Men by <hi>themſelves,</hi> and with their Patrons and Maſters, the Devils and Infernal Spirits, whoſe Work they have done, and whoſe Image they bare; and all Holy and Good Men by <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> together with Chriſt their Lord, whom they have ſerv'd, and whoſe Image is upon them. So both Parties would have it; and ſo it ſhall be. For they differing ſo vaſtly in their Tempers, ſo far as they differ, are even weary of one another here; ſo that God will certainly order a Separation of them hereafter, that they ſhall be far enough aſunder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By what hath been ſaid, it appears, That the great End of Chriſt's Death, and Reſurrection, and Government, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained upon Good Men. For <hi>God ſent his Son to Bleſs us, in turning us every one from our Iniquities.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 3.26. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.31.</note> And <hi>He hath Exalted him with his Right Hand, to be a Prince and a Saviour, to give Repentance to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and Remiſſion of Sins.</hi> His great Buſineſs was to reduce Men to their Allegiance, and to bring them back to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.</note> from whom they were departed. <hi>The Grace of God which bringeth Salvation, hath appeared to that End,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now this being done, it becomes Chriſt, as their Redeemer and Head, to take care of them, and to look after them, that they may attain the <hi>End of their Faith, the Salvation of their Souls.</hi> And ſo he aſſured us, He will do, <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.27. <hi>My Sheep hear my Voice, I know them, and they follow me; and I give unto them Eternal Life, and they ſhall never Periſh.</hi> For, ſaith he, <hi>He that hath my Commandments and keepeth them, He it is that Loveth me; and He that Loveth me, ſhall be Loved of my Father, and I will Love him, and will manifeſt my ſelf unto him,</hi> Jo. 14.21. <hi>And
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101574:11"/>
where I am, there ſhall my Servant be; and if any Man ſerve me, him will my Father Honour,</hi> Jo. 12.26. And, <hi>Father, I will that thoſe, whom thou haſt given me, be with me, where I am, that they may behold my Glory, which thou haſt given me,</hi> Jo. 17.24. They having heard, and learned of the Father, and being come unto him, He hath undertaken for them. Now they are his Members, and therefore He will not loſe them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.8.</note> They now <hi>Live unto the Lord,</hi> and ſhall <hi>Die unto the Lord, ſo that whether they Live or Die, they are the Lords;</hi> and He will certainly ſee, that they ſhall not miſcarry. For He hath Power to ſave them; <hi>all Power in Heaven and Earth being committed to him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.21.</note> So that <hi>as the Father raiſeth up the Dead, and quickneth them, ſo the Son quickneth whom he will.</hi> For <hi>as the Father hath Life in himſelf, ſo He hath given to the Son, to have Life in himſelf;</hi> and this Life he will Communicate to his Members, as it certainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns him to do. He would at laſt loſe his own Honour in the work of Redemption elſe. For it would ſeem, either that his Merit and Satisfaction are Incompetent, or that He wanted Power and good Will to do more for them. But He hath faithfully aſſured us, That <hi>He that believeth in him, tho' he were Dead, yet ſhall he Live; and whoſoever liveth and believeth in him ſhall never Die,</hi> Jo. 11.25. But <hi>becauſe I Live,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ye ſhall Live alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They being now brought to partake of thoſe Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, which make them meet for this Bleſſedneſs, they have by Vertue of God's Promiſe and Covenant alſo a Right to it.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12.</note> For it is to be <hi>an Inheritance of Saints,</hi> and they being Sanctified, are therefore become meet for it. And this is God's Covenant,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10.</note> that when He <hi>hath put his Laws into their Minds, and wrote them in their Hearts, that He will be to them a God, and they ſhall be to him a People; and that He will be merciful to their Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and their Sins and their Iniquities will He remember no more.</hi> And therefore they ſhall be freed from all that Death and Miſery, that would be the Effects and Conſequence of them. And <hi>this is the Record,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>That God hath given unto us Eternal Life, and this Life is in his Son.</hi> So that <hi>He that hath the Son,</hi> as all have, that believe in him, and ſubmit to him as their Lord and Saviour, <hi>hath Life</hi> by Vertue of God's Promiſe, <hi>and He that hath not the Son, hath not Life. For this is the Will of him that ſent me,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>That every one which ſeeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have Everlaſting Life, and I will raiſe him up at the laſt Day,</hi> Jo. 6.40.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101574:12"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I now come to the Second Thing obſerved in the Words, <hi>viz.</hi> the Nature and Parts of this Bleſſedneſs of thoſe that Die in the Lord; which if I could throughly Explain, would be an abundant Evidence of their being Bleſſed. Now this is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in two Particulars, <hi>They reſt from their Labours, and their Works do follow them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, They reſt from their Labours.</hi> Now Labour is a very toilſome and tireſome Thing, whether it be of the Body or Mind; which yet we are all here Exerciſed with, more or leſs. But the Comfort of it is, it is this World only, that is the Place for La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Work, for Pain and Sufferings; the next is the Place of Retribution and Reward, where there ſhall be no more Toil or Trouble, no more Sorrow or Pain, no more Combat or Contention with any Evil whatſoever at all.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Labours</hi> here meant in the Text, may moſt properly ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Sufferings and Perſecutions for the Faith of Chriſt; as they <hi>that Die in the Lord</hi> may moſt properly ſignifie the Holy Martyrs and Confeſſors, who ſhall for ever hereafter be freed from theſe Labours and Sufferings, for then they are all paſt the Pikes. The Devil, the Accuſer of the Brethren, the <hi>Apollyon,</hi> the <hi>Abaddon,</hi> that gives them here ſo much Diſturbance, ſhall then be far enough off from them; and neither He, nor his wicked Inſtruments, ſhall ever come near to hurt them more. For the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and Wicked Men, as you have heard, are all to be by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and there ſhall be a great Gulf fixt between them, and the Servants of God; ſo that they ſhall never be able to bring their Fire and Faggots, their Wheels and Gibbets near them there. There ſhall be <hi>nothing to hurt or deſtroy in all that Holy Mountain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if the Servants of God ſhould be freed then from all <hi>theſe kind of Labours,</hi> yet if there ſhould be any of ſome other kind for them to undergo, it could not be perfectly well with them, not could they be ſaid to be perfectly Bleſſed, which yet it is deſigned, they ſhall be. So that we may well conclude, that it is not only the Labour of Perſecutions and Martyrdoms that then they ſhall be freed from, but from all Labour and Pains whatſoever, that ſhould bring any Sufferings along with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Moſt certainly <hi>Then</hi> there ſhall be no more Labour for or about the Body, to nouriſh or feed, to maintain or preſerve it: Becauſe then there ſhall be no more weakneſs of the Body; no more Sickneſs or pained Limbs, or decay of Spirits, to ſeek a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy for. The Body indeed will not <hi>preſently</hi> after Death be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101574:12"/>
raiſed to this State of Life and Bleſſedneſs; but muſt lodge a while in the Grave, which is appointed for its Dormitory, till the Judge ſhall come, and the Trumpet ſhall ſound, to raiſe up all, that are aſleep in Jeſus. But when once it hath been ſtrained thro' the Grave, then it ſhall leave all its Corruption behind it. And it ſhall be a weak and natural Body no longer. <hi>It is ſown indeed in Weakneſs, but it is raiſed in Power; it is ſown in Corruption, but it is raiſed in Incorruption; it is ſown in Diſhonour, but it is raiſed in Glory; it is ſown a Natural Body, but it is raiſed a Spiritual Body,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.42. And therefore it ſhall not need thoſe Supports and Refreſhments then, as now it doth. Then there will be no need of Meats and Drinks to maintain it. <hi>Meats are now for the Belly, and the Belly for Meats; but God ſhall deſtroy both it, and them,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.13. For the Body then ſhall be Hale, and Well, and Strong, without them all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. Ult.</note> For <hi>He ſhall change our Vile Bodies,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>and ſhall make them like unto his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Body.</hi> When our Saviour himſelf ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41.</note> 
               <hi>That the Righteous ſhall ſhine forth as the Sun, in the Kingdom of their Father.</hi> So that tho' they ſhall have the ſame Body for Subſtance, yet not of the ſame Conſtitution, or all its parts for the ſame Offices and Purpoſes. Our Bodies then will be no more ſuch Dead and Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Things, as they are now; but Active and Vigorous, even as Spirits themſelves, and therefore without Fainting and Wearineſs. Therefore all thoſe Trades and Callings, which are here ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to provide for their Support, or to ſecure and defend them from Cold and Ill Weather, ſhall then be at an end. There we ſhall <hi>have a Building of God, an Houſe not made with Hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>Eternal in the Heavens.</hi> It ſhall never decay, or grow leaky more. There will be no Winds or Storms to annoy; no ill Airs or bad Weather; no dirty Roads, or painful Travelling; no Darkneſs or Night. For there is the Throne of God, all Lightſome, Pure, and Bliſsful, there ſhall be no Night, becauſe no need of Reſt, and yet no Wearineſs in the perpetual Day; where the Servants of God, tho' they are always at Work, yet are never tired, they ſhall be ſo Holy and Strong, and their Work ſo Good,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 48. <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.13.</note> that <hi>they reſt not Day, nor Night, ſaying, Holy, Holy, Holy, Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, which was, and is, and is to come;</hi> but are ſinging Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luja's <hi>to God, and to the Lamb for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Moreover, not only Bodily Labour, but the Labour of Study and Mortification, for the improvement and refining of our Souls, ſhall then be over likewiſe; it is a great deal of Pains and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101574:13"/>
Labour we muſt be at here, for a very ſmall Improvement. We muſt read many Books; and <hi>much Reading is a wearineſs to the Fleſh,</hi> Eccl. 12.12. as it is in the Margin: It tireth the Spirits, and impares the Health. And yet this we muſt endure in the getting of Knowledge; we muſt go through many Studies, and ſpend many weariſome Nights and Days; and be a long time, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in making Obſervations of our own, or gathering from others, before we can come almoſt to any thing. And in this we muſt ſuſtain many times a great expence of Spirits: For the Intenſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of our Minds will draw our Bodies into conſent. And the Spirits being ſo much taken up one way, there are hardly enough left many times, to diſcharge the Vital Offices of Nature. So that the Blood becomes Impoveriſh'd, the Face Pale, the Limbs Languid and Weak, and the Veſſels obſtructed within, that are the very Channels of Life. And yet after all this, it is but a little Knowledge for the moſt part, that we are able to attain unto, of any kind whatſoever. That, which we get indeed, is very Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, as little as it is. For <hi>Wiſdom exceedeth Folly, as far as Light excelleth Darkneſs,</hi> Eccl. 2.13. Yet <hi>in much Wiſdom is much Grief too, and He that encreaſeth Knowledge, encreaſeth Sorrow,</hi> Eccl. 1.18. And after all, a great deal of that Knowledge, which we ſpend ſo much of our Time about, I doubt, is hardly one degree above Folly it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But in that State hereafter, there will be none of all this Toil for the improvement of our Minds. For there is the Land of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, where we ſhall <hi>ſee God,</hi> the chief Good, <hi>as He is,</hi> and ſhall with open Face behold his Glory.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>Now we ſee but through a Glaſs darkly,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>but then Face to Face; now we know but in part, but then ſhall we know even as alſo we are known.</hi> And if we ſhall have ſuch a Viſion or Sight of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, then we may be ſure, the Knowledge of no other Thing ſhall be hid from us, as far as it may be of any uſe to us, for our Comfort and Happineſs. For he that giveth us the greater, will not withhold from us the leſs. Then we may expect to ſee and behold many Things, by an immediate Intuition, and to have a clear and plain Introſpection into their Natures and Properties. Or at leaſt, the longeſt train of Reaſoning will be eaſie and quick, Principles will be open and plain, the Impreſſions deep, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion between Things clear and apparent; ſo that the Mind will be no more in Pain, or loſe it ſelf in long or tedious Deductions. For the Powers of the Minds will be advanc'd and perfected, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101574:13"/>
ſeveral Objects diſtinct and manifeſt; Idea's of Things will be preſent to us, or ready at a Call; ſo that the turn of the Mind to its ſeveral Objects will be as eaſie, as that of the Eye is now.</p>
            <p>And thus it ſhall be for Grace and Vertue, and all the Moral Perfections of the Soul. We ſhall be troubled with none of thoſe Difficulties, that here we meet with, in the acquirement thereof. Here we muſt Work, and Work hard, to <hi>Work out our own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and muſt do it ſtill <hi>with Fear and Trembling: We muſt give all Diligence to make our Calling and Election ſure,</hi> and to add to what we have received. <hi>We muſt ſtrive to enter in at the ſtrait Gate, becauſe ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way, that leadeth to Live Everlaſting.</hi> And there can be no ſtriving without Pain: We muſt <hi>deny</hi> our Selves, <hi>and mortifie our Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which are upon the Earth.</hi> And becauſe we have not yet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, we muſt <hi>forget thoſe Things that are behind, and reach forward to thoſe Things that are before.</hi> We muſt <hi>gird up the Loins of our Minds,</hi> and ſweat and beſtir our ſelves with all our Might.</p>
            <p>It muſt be ſo here, and it cannot be otherwiſe. Becauſe our Knowledge is little and imperfect; our Affections and Appetites ſtrong to many Things, which commonly obſtruct the Divine Life. The Sollicitations of the Fleſh are ſometimes tumultuous and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement. And we have contracted many Ill Habits, which are like a ſecond Nature, and are not eaſily depoſed or laid aſide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. And the Ill Examples and Cuſtoms of the World, with the Inſinuations and Flatteries of ſome, and the Menaces and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements which we meet with from others, the Kindneſs of Carnal Friends, and the Threatnings and Fury of Enemies, are all apt to have a great Power upon us. And here, be ſure the Devil will never leave his Trade of Tempting and Seducing to Sin, as long as he can come at us. So that what from one Cauſe, and what from another, we are engaged here in a continual Fight. So that if we look no farther than Men, it is a wonder, that ever we ſhould hold out. Nor indeed could we,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</note> if we were not <hi>kept by the Power of God through Faith unto Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in that State <hi>there</hi> will be none of all this, and therefore no occaſion for all this Trouble and Pains. Becauſe then we ſhall be freed from our Errors and Miſtakes, and Miſpriſions about Things. We ſhall be freed from Evil Habits, and Evil Cuſtoms, from Inordinate Appetites and Corrupt Affections. For then we ſhall be like God. For beholding God Face to Face, <hi>we ſhall be changed into the ſame Image</hi> in a very Glorious manner. <hi>Beloved,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:101574:14"/>
ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>now we are the Sons of God, but it doth not appear, what we ſhall be; but this we know, when He ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as He is,</hi> 1 Jo. 3.2. And, ſaith St. <hi>Paul, Our Life is now hid with Chriſt in God; and when Chriſt, who is our Life, ſhall appear, then ſhall we appear alſo with him in Glory,</hi> Col. 3.3. Then we ſhall have no Fleſh to ſollicit us to Evil any more; becauſe it ſhall be chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and be no more as it is. And Evil Men and Seducers ſhall be gone; ſo that there ſhall be no more Diſcouragements or Evil Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples from them. And the Devil ſhall be caſt out, ſo that He ſhall Tempt no more. And we ſhall continually live in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God and Chriſt, and under their immediate Influences; for <hi>the Tabernacle of God ſhall be with Men,</hi> and they are to be where He is; and in the Bleſſed Company of Angels and Saints, who are all Pure and Holy; ſo that then the Servants of God ſhall have no more trouble, either to Purifie their Souls, or to keep them Pure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> And it will be a very great Addition to all, That then there ſhall be no more Labour, or Care, or Sollicitude for others neither; as here there often times muſt be. Becauſe all ſhall be then in the ſame moſt perfect and happy State. Parents ſhall be at Care for their Children no more. The Poor ſhall undergo no more hard Labour, as here they do, to provide for their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; they ſhall no more go Cold, or fare Hard, for want of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Proviſions. For there ſhall be no Poor in Heaven; but all, Kings and Princes, ſitting upon their Thrones of Glory. For it is their <hi>Fathers good Pleaſure to give them a Kingdom.</hi> There will be no more need of thoſe Things, which now we are forc'd to take ſuch Care about, in this Imperfect and Animal State. And there will be no Enemies to Invade, or Extort from us what we have. Nor ſhall we need to be at any Concern to Guard our ſelves againſt the Violence or Malice of thoſe, that would deſpoil or raviſh away our Comforts from us. For none of them all ſhall come there.</p>
            <p>Then Private and Publick Labours ſhall be all over. There ſhall be no more Labour to preſerve, or purge the Church from any of thoſe Things, that now do ſo much annoy it. For then there will be no Errors or Hereſies to Corrupt it; no Schiſms or Factions to divide it; no Animoſities or Quarrels, Heart-Burnings, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions to diſturb its Peace. For then Chriſt <hi>ſhall preſent it to himſelf a Glorious Church, not having Spot or Wrinkle, or any ſuch Thing,</hi> Eph. 5.27.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101574:14"/>And then there ſhall be as little Labour, to preſerve the Peace or Quiet of Government, from Tyranny or Invaſion, from Men of Fraud and Violence, of furious Paſſions and unbridled Luſts. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there ſhall be no ſuch there. And all ſhall be under the moſt perfect and immediate Rule and Government of God himſelf, who ſhall be with them, and dwell among them. And all ſhall perfectly Love their Governour, and his Government; and ſhall <hi>Love one another, with a Pure Heart fervently.</hi> Oh Bleſſed State, and Bleſſed Condition, when all this Trouble of every Kind ſhall be at an end! Yet ſo it ſhall be then.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Their Works do follow them.</hi> That is, the Reward of their Works; for ſo it muſt needs be underſtood. Some in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed underſtand it of the good Effects of all the Sufferings of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors and Martyrs in this Life, in the Fall of the Man of Sin, and bringing down the preſent Kingdom of Darkneſs. But this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here Aſſigned as part of their Bleſſedneſs, it ſeems to me that it muſt ſignifie a Reward to themſelves; and can mean no leſs, than God's Approbation of what they have done in his Service, and for his Name, and the Reward that He gives them thereupon.</p>
            <p>It is indeed a Reward of Grace, and it is ſo Tranſcendant, and ſurpaſſing all that they have done and ſuffered; that, as the Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>The Sufferings of this preſent time are not worthy to be compared with the Glory, that ſhall be revealed in them.</hi> And <hi>theſe light Afflictions, which are but for a moment,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>work for them a far more exceeding and eternal Weight of Glory,</hi> as was alſo obſerved before. However, a Reward it is, and that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs, not only to thoſe that in the ſtricteſt Senſe <hi>Die in,</hi> or <hi>for the Lord;</hi> but alſo to all the Faithful Servants of Chriſt, who may be truly ſaid likewiſe to <hi>Depart hence in the Lord,</hi> in his Faith and Service, in Relation to him, and Union with him, as their Lord and Head. So that <hi>Verily Men ſhall ſay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 58.11.</note> 
               <hi>there is a Reward of the Righteous.</hi> And therefore, <hi>ſay to the Righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſ.</hi> 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>it ſhall be well with him; for they ſhall Eat the Fruit of their Doings.</hi> For <hi>God ſhall reward every Man according to his Works.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27.</note> But here is the Place of Work, and then hereafter of Reward. When <hi>whatever any Man hath done heartily, as to the Lord; He ſhall receive for it the Reward of the Inheritance,</hi> Col. 3.24. So that in this World there is Striving, and Fighting, and Working, and then is the time of Recompence for all their Work and Labour of Love, which they ſhall find <hi>ſhall not be in vain in the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. Ult.</note> And this ſhall be ſo great, that it is a time of Coronation and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101574:15"/>
Glory to them, when it ſhall appear, what ſhall be <hi>done to the Men whom God will Honour.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4.</note> For they <hi>ſhall receive a Crown of Glory, which fadeth not away.</hi> For, <hi>be thou faithful unto Death,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>and I will give thee a Crown of Life,</hi> Rev. 2.10. Then they come to receive their Robes, and to have Palms of Triumph in their Hands, and to be ſet upon Thrones of Glory. For, <hi>to him that overcometh,</hi> ſaith He, <hi>will I grant to ſit with me on my Throne, even as I alſo overcame, and am ſet down with my Father on his Throne,</hi> Rev. 3.21. And this ſhall be the Portion of all the Faithlul Servants of God. For, <hi>God will render to every Man,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>according to his Deeds; to them, who by patient continuance in well Doing, ſeek for Glory, Honour and Immortality, He will give Eternal Life,</hi> Rom. 2.6.</p>
            <p>This indeed is all of Grace; but therefore, becauſe it is of Grace, it ſhall be ſo much the greater. For if it were to be given in proportion to our Merit, then it could be but little; becauſe our Merit is but little, or rather, properly ſpeaking, none at all. But now being to be of Grace, it will therefore be exceeding great; to ſet forth the Glory and Love of God, who as a great King, will give like himſelf; and to ſet forth the Price of our Redemer's Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and to ſhew how high and valuable they are.</p>
            <p>This is moſt certain for <hi>One Thing,</hi> that there will be a moſt intimate and tranſporting Manifeſtation of the Ever-bleſſed God himſelf to his Beloved People. Then they ſhall not only ſee his <hi>Back Parts,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, that is, ſome little and low degree of Splendor and Beauty, but then they ſhall ſee him with open Face, in his higheſt Luſtre, and moſt inconceivable Glory. Then they ſhall ſee Chriſt in all his Glory, and they ſhall be <hi>with him.</hi> Then is the time of the great Supper of the Lamb, when He will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt and diſplay himſelf in all his Lovelineſs and Beauty to all about him. Here is the place of Faith and Hope; but there is the place of Viſion and Fruition. Here we ſip a little by the way; as in a Land of Drought; but we are not yet come to the <hi>Rivers of Pleaſure;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 16.11.</note> they are <hi>at God's Right Hand, in whoſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is fulneſs of Joy;</hi> ſo that there the Saints and Servants of God ſhall never Hunger or Thirſt more. Here we have the Taſtes and firſt Fruits of the Spirit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.14.</note> as a Pledge and Earneſt in the way; but there is the full Enjoyment of the <hi>Purchaſed Poſſeſſion.</hi> We cannot expect here ſo much in the way, as when we come to our Father's Houſe. Here we are but at the Footſtool; it can't be with us now, as when we come to the Throne of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101574:15"/>Yea, ſuch is our State here, That we muſt be tried, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplined, and Corrected ſometimes; there is a Neceſſity ſometimes for it. And therefore <hi>if need be, for a Seaſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>we are in Heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, through manifold Temptations.</hi> We are Sinners, and live among Sinners, and therefore ſometimes we muſt expect Sinners fare. Our Corruptions muſt be melted down in the Furnace of Affliction, when there is no other way to purge us from them. And our Father muſt ſometimes Frown upon us, and Chaſtiſe us, becauſe the Beſt of us all are ſometimes apt to be wandring and neglectful of our Duty. <hi>Before I was Afflicted,</hi> the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, <hi>I went aſtray; but now have I learned thy Ways.</hi> Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions tend to File and Poliſh us, to clear us of the Ruſt and Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh that is apt to cleave unto us.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.10.</note> God <hi>Chaſtens us</hi> therefore <hi>for our Profit, that we might be Partakers of this Holineſs. For tho' no Chaſtning for the preſent ſeems to be Joyous, but Grievous; nevertheleſs afterwards it yieldeth the peaceable Fruits of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to them, that are Exerciſed thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then hereafter there will be no occaſion for any of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline any more; becauſe of that perfect Transformation into the Image and Likeneſs of God, which then his People ſhall have. For <hi>his Servants ſhall ſerve him, and they ſhall ſee his Face,</hi> Rev. 22.3. So that there will be the fulneſs of Light and Love; and God ſhall never withdraw from them the Light of his Countenance any more.</p>
            <p>I have not time to tell you, as much as I might, what all the Reward will be. And beſides, I have prevented my ſelf in part already, in what I have ſaid before. Only in ſhort, it will be <hi>A State of all Perfection.</hi> And that is enough. For there is the <hi>General Aſſembly of the Church of the Firſt-Born, and the Spirits of Juſt Men made Perfect,</hi> Heb. 12.23. So then, That <hi>which is Perfect ſhall come, and that which is in part, ſhall be done away,</hi> 1 Cor. 13.10. Where the Apoſtle doth certainly mean a Perfection of Knowledge and Grace, of that Divine Grace of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which He elſewhere tells us, is the <hi>Fulfilling of the Law.</hi> And that muſt needs imply an Enlargement and Perfection of our Faculties, and a Cure of all their Weakneſs and Infirmities. For full and perfect Habits of Light and Good in the Mind and Heart, can never ſubſiſt without a full Extention and Purification thereof. And then from thence we may certainly infer, that there ſhall be a perfect Communication of Good, to anſwer to the fulneſs of their Enlargement. Or elſe the Enlargement of our Faculties would
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101574:16"/>
rather be a Torment and Vexation, than a Satisfaction, if they have not Objects proper to ſuit them. And from all this there muſt needs flow an intire and unſpeakable <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> a fulneſs of Delight and Pleaſure running over in the Soul. To which this will be a wonderful Addition, the conſideration of the everlaſting Duration and Continuance of all this Bleſſedneſs. That it ſhall for ever continue without Interruption, Intermiſſion or Decay. For ſo it ſhall be,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.</note> for as much as we <hi>ſhall for ever be with the Lord,</hi> who will for ever Delight in his People, ever take Care of them, and be a Guard to them, that no Evil ſhall come near them. Oh Bleſſed Day, and Bleſſed State, when all this Good ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to them! But when will all this be?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I now proceed therefore to the Third Thing, obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the Words, which is the time of the beginning, or the Commencement of this Happineſs; which ſhall be <hi>Henceforth, i. e.</hi> from the very Day or time of their Death, or Departure out of this World. Not that they ſhall be preſently inſtated in all that full Poſſeſſion of Good which I have mention'd; which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, whilſt their Bodies remain ſtill in the Grave, or before the Reſurrection. Therefore the full Poſſeſſion or Perfection of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, is not to be expected till the Coming of Our Lord; as the Scripture generally ſets it forth to us.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4.</note> But <hi>when Chriſt, who is our Life, ſhall appear, then ſhall we appear with him in Glory.</hi> But yet this Happineſs is to begin on the Day of the Saints Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution; <hi>Henceforth,</hi> from the very time of their Death. They ſhall Reſt from all their Labours preſently, and their Reward doth then begin: I know there are other Senſes given of this Expreſſion; but I can ſee nothing but this, that anſwers the Deſign of comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Afflicted Servants of God in their preſent Sufferings, which this Text is intended for. There is nothing but this Poſſeſſion of the Reward at Death, can denominate them Bleſſed from <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they might Glorifie God in this World, tho' it were in Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, yet they would rather deſire to do ſo, than be gone hence, unleſs they may come to the preſent Enjoyment of their Happineſs. How are they Bleſſed from <hi>Henceforth,</hi> in having the Reward of their Works, if there be no ſuch Reward yet to be enjoyed? If the Soul were to ſleep in the Grave in a lumpiſh and unactive State, where then would be their Bleſſedneſs? It were better to continue longer here, in performance of their Maſter's Work, and in the Service of their Lord, as long as God ſhall be pleaſed to uphold
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101574:16"/>
them, and enable them to hold out in it, tho' it were in the midſt of Labour and Suffering. And they would chuſe to do ſo, becauſe hereby they would further their Reward hereafter; when God ſhall Reward Men, not only according to the Nature, but alſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Meaſure and Degree of their Labour and Sufferings: All the Troubles and Labours of this Life therefore would rather be endured a great deal, than One would chuſe to be put into an inſenſible and unactive State, where there is neither Work, nor Enjoyment; no One, that hath any thing of Chriſtian Zeal and Magnanimity would be glad to be removed hence, ſo long as God is pleaſed to give him Strength and Patience to hold out, unleſs He might immediately paſs to the Enjoyment of that Happineſs, which is the End of all his preſent Seeking, and Striving, and Labouring.</p>
            <p>It was this that put St. <hi>Paul</hi> into ſuch a Strait, that he knew not which to chuſe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21. <hi>For to me to Live is Chriſt,</hi> ſaith he, He being heartily devoted to him, and being glad to be employed in his Service; but then <hi>to Die was preſent Gain.</hi> For that He muſt mean, or elſe it had been better, and more Gain to live ſtill. <hi>For if I Live in the Fleſh, this is the Fruit of my Labour,</hi> to be ſerviceable to Chriſt in the Converſion of more to him; <hi>Yet what I ſhall chuſe, I know not.</hi> Why? Would not the Apoſtle chuſe to ſerve Chriſt in the Work of the Goſpel, rather than ceaſe to be? <hi>But I am in a Strait betwixt two, having a Deſire to deport,</hi> and to launch out from this Body and this World; <hi>and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</hi> That was the Reaſon why He was willing to be gone from the Body, becauſe then he was to be with Chriſt; and that would be far better for him. For in this the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle is very Poſitive and Peremptory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. <hi>For we know,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>if our Earthly Houſe of this Tabernacle,</hi> the Body, <hi>were diſſolved, we have</hi> a better Dwelling for our Spirit prepared, <hi>a Building of God, an Habitation</hi> in the Heavenly Glory, <hi>an Houſe not made with Hands,</hi> of Mens or Mortal Facture or Procreation, <hi>Eternal</hi> and undecaying there. And <hi>in this therefore we Groan earneſtly, and deſire to be clothed upon with that our Houſe, which is from Heaven. Knowing,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. <hi>that whilſt we are at home in the Body, we are abſent from the Lord; therefore are willing rather, to be abſent from the Body, and to be preſent with the Lord.</hi> So that it ſeems the Souls of Good Men at Death are to leave the Body, and then be abſent from it; and then they are forthwith to be preſent with Chriſt. So 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. <hi>Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101574:17"/>
the Righteous Judge ſhall give me at that Day.</hi> And what Day was that? But the <hi>Day of his Departure,</hi> of which he ſpeaks, <hi>Ver.</hi> 6. and ſaith was then <hi>ready at Hand.</hi> And that we may not think, that this was only a Priviledge belonging to him, or to ſuch Excellent Perſons, as he was, He adds, <hi>and not to me only, but alſo to all them, that Love his appearing.</hi> So that we ſee, that this is a Bleſſing, that all the Faithful Servants and Followers of Chriſt ſhall partake of, as well as the Bleſſed Apoſtle himſelf.</p>
            <p>Now the Enjoyment of this Happineſs in the Regions above, I do not only in Charity hope, as I would of every ordinary Good Chriſtian; but do moſt firmly believe, is the State and Condition of this Reverend and Good Man, whoſe Relicks we have now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, and upon the occaſion of the Interment of which we are here met. Of whom therefore I cannot but ſay ſomething, tho' not near ſo much, as his Character, I believe, doth deſerve; my Acquaintance with him having been ſo long Interrupted, as for ſome Years.</p>
            <p>He ſeemed to me to be an Aged Perſon, when I firſt knew him; but by Temperance and Wiſe Conduct, and the Bleſſing of God thereupon, and by the Divine Protection warding off Evil Harms and Accidents from him, which might either have cut him off, or broken his Health much ſooner, how hath his Life been prolonged to almoſt half the common Age of Man ſince that time? It being now towards Thirty Years ago ſince I was firſt acquainted with him.</p>
            <p>That which I had always obſerved in him, was a great Kindneſs and Benignity of Diſpoſition, joined with an Undiſſembled Integrity and Uprightneſs; whereby I dare ſay, he wiſh'd Well to all Men, and bore a Loving Reſpect in his Carriage to all, and rejoic'd in all Men's Welfare and Happineſs; and was glad, when He could himſelf any ways promote it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This, I doubt not, he had learned from his Great Lord and Maſter, who was kind unto all, and who by his Pattern and Precepts had made Univerſal Love the great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of his Religion. And by this means, one would think, He could not have many Enemies. For who could find in their Hearts to be Enemies to one, in whom there was reſplendent ſo much Goodneſs? And this Goodneſs was ſet off by a profound Humility, and low Condeſcenſion and Reſpect to the Meaneſt the Loweſt, the Leaſt. By this He was apt to prefer others before himſelf, and to ſet a Value upon the Parts and Performances of ſome Young Perſons above his own Gray headed Knowledge and Experience.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101574:17"/>
By this Kindneſs and Humility, his Self-diſtruſt and Self-abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, He was preſerved from the Fiery and Furious Zeal, which is the Blemiſh of ſome of all Parties, that differ in ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials of Religion and Worſhip. He could not imagine, why a Difference in ſome Circumſtantials, ſhould make Men Hate and Curſe one another, among whom there was a good Accord in the Main and Subſtantial Points of Chriſtian Doctrine. Therefore He could bear a Kind and Friendly Reſpect to other Good Men of other Perſwaſions beſides his own, as He would hope for the like from them.</p>
            <p>He had a great Calmneſs in his own Temper, but He was For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Fervent in Spirit, in the Service of his God; as appeared in his Devotions in a Private, but much Honoured Family, where I have heard him. And his long and continu'd Labour in the Service of God, in that Way wherein He thought He might Glorifie God, even to extreme Old Age, is a great Inſtance of his Delight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, of his Pious Zeal for the promoting of Religion, and of his Earneſt Deſire of the Eternal Welfare of Men. He always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to me to be one of Eminent Piety, of Exact Walking, of an Healing Spirit, and to be full of Love to God, and Good Men of different Denominations. He was not for a Wrangling or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putative Divinity, which tends to Gender Strife; but for Plain, Practical Godlineſs in its Life and Power, which hath always in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed moſt Sweetneſs in it, and ſo will eſpecially appear to have at the laſt.</p>
            <p>His Afflictions, I hear, in many Reſpects, have been many, but that his Faith and Patience alſo have been as Eminent. Wherein He deſerves, as in many other Things, your Pious Imitation. In a Word, He Lived long in the Exerciſe of Piety towards God, and of Good Will to Men; and how He Died, you know.</p>
            <p>I could gladly have enlarged much more upon his Character; but theſe few Things, I could not but mention, being always bound to have his Memory in Honour. For I muſt ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I have had him of Old in many Reſpects my Friend, in ſome Reſpects as my Father and Patron, and in ſome others a Guide and Director, when I firſt entred my ſelf upon this Sacred Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. This Acknowledgment I cannot but take this Opportunity to expreſs; nor do I know any juſt Reflections, that any can make upon it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now only make an Inference or two from what I have ſaid on the foregoing Subject, and then Conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101574:18"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To Comfort, and Prepare Good Men for the Expectation of their Death, that they may not be Frighted at the Approach of it, as ſuch a Dreadful Thing; it being moſt certain, that when they remove out of this Tabernacle, they enter into an Eſtate of preſent Bliſs in the preſence of their Lord.</p>
            <p>If the Soul indeed were to lye in a ſtupid Lethargy in the Grave, and have no more Senſe or Reflection, or Enjoyment after the time of Diſſolution, they ſhould deſire to continue here as long as they can, that they may bring more Honour to God in the World, and ſo might further their Reward hereafter thereby. And they might have juſt Cauſe to take Death for their Enemy, whenſoever it comes, that ſhould deprive them of ſo great Advantages here, and bring them none in the room. But there is no fear of all this. The Soul is an Active Spark, the Breath of the Almighty; which, whilſt it is in the Body, by the Laws of Union that were fix'd in the Original Creation by the great Creator, muſt ſympathize with it. But when the Body is no longer a tolerable Habitation for it, it will then Diſlodge, and take its Flight, and the Holy Angels wait to carry it aloft, through all the Airy Armies of inviſible Fiends, to place it above, out of the reach of all their Malice. For the Soul is a Thinking Subſtance, which hath no Relation to Matter; but is of another Nature from it, and hath quite other Properties in its Idea. And being Immaterial, it is not ſubject to Putrifaction or Diſſolution of Parts, becauſe it hath no Parts, and therefore none to be diſſolved, but muſt in its own Nature Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and Live ſtill. But whatever the Philoſophy of the Soul may be, we have full aſſurance from Divine Revelation of its continued Life, and greater Perfection and Enjoyment after Death than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28.</note> Our Saviour told his Diſciples, That <hi>Men, tho' they might kill the Body, yet were not able to kill the Soul,</hi> and therefore bid them not be affraid of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note>
               <hi>The Body indeed muſt Die, becauſe of Sin;</hi> but the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the better part, <hi>is Life, becauſe of Righteouſneſs.</hi> So that Good Men have no Cauſe to be mightily Affrighted at the Approach of Death. For tho' it be the King of Terrors to outward appearance, yet they may look upon it, as a Routed or Conquered Enemy, as a Serpent, that hath loſt its Sting and Strength, which howſoever it may Hiſs, and ſhow its Rage and Fury, yet cannot hurt. So that Good Men may Triumph over it, and over all Things elſe beſides; becauſe <hi>neither Death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38.</note> 
               <hi>nor Life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor Things preſent, nor Things to come, nor Height,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101574:18"/>
nor Depth, nor any other Creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate them from the Love of God, which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord. But in and over all theſe Things, they are more than Conquerors, through him that Loved them.</hi> Death is now rather a Friend to them, the Meſſenger of the great King, to invite them to his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which he hath prepared for them.</p>
            <p>The ſame Comfort there is at the Departure of Others, Friends and Relations, that Die in the Lord. For now they are paſt from all their Labours and Troubles, from all their Fears and Dangers, their Pains and Sufferings whatſoever, and are gone but to take Poſſeſſion of the Promiſed Crown. It is a Loſs to us indeed, that they are gone; and Self-Love makes us to Mourn and Complain at it. But what do <hi>They</hi> loſe, in leaving us, or the World; and the little Accommodations of this Life, that are now entered upon the Poſſeſſion of the Inheritance. Tho' we loſe by them, becauſe they are gone, yet we ought not ſure to Grudge at their Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To Exhort all to the Faith and Service of Chriſt our Lord, that they may alſo <hi>Die in him,</hi> and ſo be Bleſſed. For we muſt certainly Live to him now, if we will <hi>Die in him,</hi> or be Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him at the laſt. We muſt have Union with him in Life, as our Lord and Head, if we think to have Union with him, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to him at Death, as our Everlaſting Saviour. We can by no means expect to Live with God hereafter, if we will not Live to his Honour here. We can never expect, that He will receive us into his Embraces at laſt, if we continue now in an Hatred of him, and Enmity againſt him. Neither the Work, nor Enjoyments of Heaven, can be ſuitable to an Unholy Soul, that is not Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed into the Divine Likeneſs. For what ſhould ſuch an One do with God, or among the Saints above, that hath nothing at all of a Divine or Saint-like Nature? But if we are now made like God, and Live to him, He will be ſure then to take Care of his Own. For <hi>the Foundation,</hi> or Covenant <hi>of God, ſtandeth ſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>having this Seal, the Lord knoweth them that are his. And, let every One that nameth the Name of Chriſt, depart from Iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let all Wicked Men ſee therefore the abſolute Neceſſity, and the great Advantages of Religion. They are apt now to have hard Thoughts of it, and to Cenſure it ſore for a very Soure and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholly Thing; tho' that is a very great Miſtake and Miſpriſion; but how will it be at laſt? Or what will their Thoughts be of it hereafter? Then they will find, that this had been the only way
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101574:19"/>
to Happineſs and Bliſs, whatever they think of it now. And ſhould not Wiſe Men have Futurity in Account, as well as the preſent Time? Should they look only at their preſent Pleaſures and Advantages, and neglect the future, which are infinitely greater? Or do they think to Die the Death of the Righteous, and yet will not Live his Life? This cannot be.</p>
            <p>But you muſt begin now, and ſhould not put off the Study of Piety and Holineſs, till hereafter neither. You Young Ones muſt not think to Live to the Age that this Holy Man of God hath done. This is a rare and peculiar Favour, which very few can expect. You may be called and ſummon'd away before you are aware. However, can you ever begin to be Wiſe too ſoon, or Bleſſed too ſoon? For this is certain, that you are never Wiſe, or Bleſſed, but in the way of Religion. And yet how apt are the moſt to put this off ſtill, and to cry, 'tis too ſoon yet, 'tis too ſoon yet. Yet <hi>a little more Sleep, and a little more Slumber, and a little more folding of the Hands to Sleep.</hi> A little more of the Pleaſures and Vanities of Sin; a little more unjuſt Gain, and then we will take up, and Repent; and Return. And yet when the Time is come, that they have ſet, they are as backward to it as before, or worſe. Their Hearts are more Hardned, and they are farther off from Repentance and Religion, than they were ſome Years ago. And will you always be thus deceived?</p>
            <p>You that continue in Sin, and the Impenitency of your Hearts, what do you think to do at laſt? Where will you appear? Do you expect that Chriſt ſhould take you to himſelf, Dying in your Rebellion againſt him, or that He ſhould ſave you in your Sins? How unreaſonable is this?</p>
            <p>Repent, Oh Sinners! And Return in Time. And let thoſe who have, begun Well, hold on ſtill, left they loſe their Reward. The Day of our Redemption draweth near. Therefore let us caſt off the Works of Darkneſs; let us keep down Sin, which Chriſt came to deſtroy. Let us Renounce our own Luſts and Wills, and Live as his Covenant Servants; and then Bleſſed ſhall we be.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
